<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses and Aaron or the affinitie of ciuill and ecclesiasticke power A sermon intended for the Parliament held at Oxon, August 7. 1625. But by reason of the sudden and vnhappy dissolution, then, not preach't, but since vpon occasion, was; at St. Maries in Oxford, the 26. of February. 1625. [sic] By Humphry Sydenham Mr. of Arts, and fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13268</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101844</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837647</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837647</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1984</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13268)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1984)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1396:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Moses and Aaron or the affinitie of ciuill and ecclesiasticke power A sermon intended for the Parliament held at Oxon, August 7. 1625. But by reason of the sudden and vnhappy dissolution, then, not preach't, but since vpon occasion, was; at St. Maries in Oxford, the 26. of February. 1625. [sic] By Humphry Sydenham Mr. of Arts, and fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Eliot's Court Press] for Iohn Parker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also issued as part of his "Five sermons, upon severall occasions", STC 23563.</note>
                  <note>Printer from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Central Library (Bristol, Eng.).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1984:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1984:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MOSES and AARON OR THE AFFINITIE OF Ciuill and Eccleſiaſticke power.</p>
            <p>A SERMON INTENDED <hi>for the Parliament held at</hi> Oxon, Auguſt. 7. 1625.</p>
            <p>But by reaſon of the ſudden and vnhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py diſſolution, then, not preach't, but ſince vpon occaſion, was; at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. MARIES in Oxford, the 26. of <hi>February.</hi> 1625.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>Humphry Sydenham</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> of <hi>Arts,</hi> and Fellow of WADHAM <hi>Colledge</hi> in OXFORD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for IOHN PARKER. 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1984:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1984:2"/>
            <head>TO MY MVCH DESERVING FRIEND AND BROTHER, FRANCIS GODOLPHIN, <hi>Eſquire, This.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY DEARE SIR;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hil'ſt others declaime (too iuſtly) againſt the <hi>dull charities</hi> of the <hi>times,</hi> and the <hi>coldneſſe of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in their <hi>Allies,</hi> and <hi>bloud,</hi> I cannot but magnifie <hi>their</hi> worth, in <hi>you,</hi> where I haue met a <hi>vertue,</hi> ſcarce ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ampled by a ſecond, <hi>friendſhip in a brother.</hi> I thought it a high iniuſtice to ſmoother ſuch a <hi>miracle,</hi> and therefore haue heere ſet it vpon
<pb facs="tcp:1984:3"/>
               <hi>record;</hi> that, as the <hi>age</hi> may bluſh at her other <hi>prodigies,</hi> ſo glory heere, that ſhe hath (at length) brought forth <hi>one</hi> who hath not loſt either his <hi>Nature</hi> to his <hi>alliance,</hi> or <hi>piety</hi> to his <hi>Countrey.</hi> A goodneſſe ſeldome paralell'd in theſe dayes of ours, theſe degenerate dayes of ours, when we may finde a more <hi>naturall</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence, a liuelier heat of affection, amongſt thoſe of ſauage and barbarous condition, than in the boſome of our owne <hi>Tribe</hi> and <hi>Nation.</hi> But I may not taxe, when I am to ſalute, 'tis out of the roade of <hi>gratulation; this</hi> is intended ſo, A meere <hi>declaration</hi> of my <hi>thankfulnes</hi> for all thoſe your <hi>noble</hi> Offices of a <hi>reall brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> which though I haue not <hi>power</hi> (as yet) to <hi>ſatisfie,</hi> I ſhall haue euer <hi>will</hi> to <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> and in that <hi>loyaltie</hi> I perſiſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt reſpectfully engag'd, HVM: SYDENHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:1984:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Moſes and Aaron OR</hi> The affinitie of Ciuill and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticke power.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EXOD. 4.12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Goe, and I will be in thy mouth, and teach thee what thou ſhalt ſay.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow ſtrangely God compaſſes what he proiects for his, by the hands of an obſcure Agent?<note place="margin">Cap. 3. v. 9.10.</note> 
               <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> hath beene long enough vnder the groanes of <hi>Egypt,</hi> it ſhall bee now vnyoakt from that heauie ſeruitude; and this muſt bee done by no troden meanes, or ordinary inſtrument,<note place="margin">Cap. 3.8.</note> But one that <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Egypt</hi> too ſhall ſtand amaz'd at to ſee in ſuch a power of ſubſtitution, <hi>A ſhepheard. Moſes</hi> a fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1984:4"/>his fathers flocke, not farre from <hi>Horeb,</hi> the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine of the Lord,<note place="margin">Cap. 3.1. Cap. 3.4.</note> when ſuddenly a voice doth at once aſtoniſh and inuite him, <hi>Moſes, Moſes.</hi> 'T ſhould ſeeme the affaires were both of neceſſitie and diſpatch, when the perſon to be imployed was thus preſt by a double ſummons:<note place="margin">Cap. 4.18.</note> what ſhall he doe now? <hi>His flocke</hi> muſt bee <hi>left with Iethro in Midian,</hi> and he ſhall <hi>to Court,</hi> there to ranſome an engag'd and captiu'd Nation, from the ſhac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles of a Tyrant;<note place="margin">Cap. 2.17.</note> A ſimple deſigne for one ſeaſon'd in the courſe conditions of an <hi>Hebrew</hi> and a <hi>Midianite:</hi> Men knowne more by the largeneſſe of their folds, than any eminence for matters of ſtate, moſt of them being heardſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, or ſhepheards. But ſee how God will extract won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders out of improbabilities, and miracles out of both: <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhall firſt ſee one,<note place="margin">Cap. 3.2. Cap. 3.3.</note> &amp; then, do many. <hi>Behold an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell of the Lord in a flaming fire in a buſh, the buſh burned</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>and the Buſh was not conſumed.</hi> A viſion as ſtrange as the proiect he is now ſet vpon, and doth not ſo much take, as ſtagger him. That it burned and conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med not, raniſhes his eies only, how it ſhould burn &amp; not conſume, his intellectualls; So that he is now doubly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranced, in the ſenſe, &amp; in the thought. But there is more of myſtery inuol'd here than the Prophet yet dreames of or diſcouers. God in his affaires requires both heat, and conſtancie: men of cold and languiſhing reſolution are not fit ſubiects for his imploiments, but thoſe which can withſtand the ſhocke of many a fiery triall; they whoſe zeale can burne cheerfully in the ſeruices of their God and not conſume. <hi>Moſes,</hi> therfore ſhall now to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> with as many terrours as meſſages.<note place="margin">Cap. 5. verſ. 6, 7, 8, 9.</note> Ten times hee muſt bid the Tyrant let <hi>Iſrael</hi> goe: euery Iniunction ſhall find a repulſe, euery repulſe, a plague, and euery plague, a wonder. Somewhat a harſh embaſſie to a King, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be welcom'd but with a ſtorme, whoſe diſpoſition is as impatient of rebuke, as not inur'd too't. Thoſe eares which haue been ſleekt hitherto with the ſupple dialect
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1984:4"/>of the Court, (that oile of Sycophants and temporizers) will not be roug'ht now with the courſe phraſe of a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, much leſſe, of menacing. There's no dallying with the eye of a cock atrice; I am ſure none, with the paw of a Lion; Ruine ſits on the brow of offended Soueraigntie, each looke ſparkles indignation, and that indignation, death. <hi>Moſes</hi> is now ſtartled at the imployment,<note place="margin">Cap. 3.11. Cap. 4.10.</note> and begins both to expoſtulate and repine. —<hi>Who am I that I ſhould goe vnto Pharaoh? I am not eloquent, but of ſlow ſpeech and of a ſlow tongue—?</hi> Good Lord! In a Prophet what a piece of modeſtie with diſtruſt? will God employ any whom he will not accommodate? Hee hath now thrice perſwaded <hi>Moſes</hi> to this great vndertaking. The other as often manifeſts his vnwillingneſſe by excuſe, as if he would either diſpute Gods prouidence, or queſtion his ſupply. We find therefore this diffidence check't with a new inſinuation of rectifying all defects.<note place="margin">Cap. 4.10.</note> —<hi>Who hath made mans mouth, or who makes the dumbe or the deafe, or the ſeeing, or the blinde, haue not I the Lord?</hi> Why ſhould any further ſcruple or doubt aſſaile thee? I that am the God of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> will protect thee; let no wauerings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or terrours of <hi>Egypt</hi> any way diſmay thee: par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular infirmities in thine owne perſon I will mould anew to perfection, or if thoſe vacillations and ſtutterings of the tongue yet diſhearten thee,<note place="margin">Cap. 14.14.</note> 
               <hi>Loe Aaron the Levite is thy brother, I know that he can ſpeake well, take him with thee, and this rod too,</hi> wherewith thou ſhalt doe wonders as dreadfull as vnpattern'd. Deliuer <hi>Pharaoh</hi> roundly my commands, if he will not vndeafe his care vpon their firſt Alarum, I will bore it with my thunder. Why ſtandeſt thou then any longer ſo diuided? <hi>Goe now, and I will be in thy mouth, and teach thee what thou ſhalt ſay</hi>—.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> is diſpatch't now, hath his commiſſion ſeal'd, each particle of his meſſage punctually deliuered him,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1984:5"/>wherein (as in all ſaecular and ſubordinate Embaſſies) we finde <hi>A command,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diuiſion.</note> 
               <hi>A direction, and a Promiſe.</hi> The <hi>command, Goe;</hi> The <hi>Promiſe, I will be in thy mouth;</hi> The <hi>Direction, teach thee what thou ſhalt ſay.</hi> So he that is ſingled out to any ſeruice of his God for the aduantage of his Iſrael, muſt not giue backe or wauer, <hi>Goe</hi>—. If a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling obedience ſecond this command, God promiſes to aſſiſt, <hi>I will be in thy mouth;</hi> if there, be not daſh't at the ſlowneſſe or vnprouidedneſſe of thy ſpeech, <hi>I will teach thee what thou ſhalt ſay.</hi> Once more is there a retyred worth, which deſires to ſit downe to obſcurity, and ſeemes vnwilling to the publike ſeruices of his God, heareſt thou not this <hi>proficiſcere</hi> from heauen? <hi>Goe.</hi> But haſt thou once vndertooke them? be not diſcourag'd, here's an —<hi>aperiam,</hi> too—. <hi>I will be in thy mouth;</hi> but am I welcom'd there with reuerence, and awe? ſpeake bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly then, for, <hi>Ego inſtruam, I will teach thee what thou ſhalt ſay—, Goe then.</hi> But let's firſt cleare the paſſage. 'Tis not my intent to ſhew you <hi>Moſes</hi> here in the ſtormes and troubles of the <hi>Court</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> but of the <hi>Church.</hi> I may not bee too buſie with the <hi>riddles</hi> and <hi>Labyrinth's</hi> of the two firſt; the times are both rough and touchie, I will onely ſhew you a farre off, how this <hi>Proteus</hi> and that <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melion</hi> vary both their <hi>ſhape</hi> and <hi>colour. Moſes</hi> was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed forty yeares a <hi>Courtier,</hi> and the better <hi>part</hi> of his life a <hi>Stateſman,</hi> yet he was a <hi>Prieſt</hi> too (and ſo I follow him) if you dare take the authoritie of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> who though on his ſecond booke on <hi>Exod.</hi> 10. <hi>quaſt. giues Moſes</hi> barely <hi>Principatum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>2.</hi> in Exod. quaeſt. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Aaron miniſterium,</hi> yet in his Commentaries on the 98 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> he thus interrogates, <hi>Si Moſes Sacordos non erat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>98.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quid erat? numquid maior Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdote?</hi> and the ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> put's <hi>Samuel</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them that <hi>call vpon Gods Name,</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> amongſt the <hi>Prieſts, Pſal.</hi> 99.6.— I haue now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mou'd all rubs and obſtacles, the way is ſmooth and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable, what ſhould then hinder <hi>Moſes</hi> any longer, <hi>Goe,</hi>—.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:1984:5"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Command</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> are the <hi>bodie</hi> and <hi>ſoule</hi> of <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſocietie,</hi> the <hi>head</hi> and <hi>foote</hi> of an <hi>eſtabliſh't Empire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pars <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Command</hi> ſits as <hi>Soueraigne</hi> and hath three Scepters, by which it rules, <hi>Authoritie, Courage, Sufficiencie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obedience,</hi> as 'ewere the <hi>ſubiect,</hi> and beares vp it's alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance with three pillars, <hi>neceſſitie, profit, willingneſſe.</hi> Sometimes <hi>command</hi> growes impetuous and rough, and then 'tis no more <hi>Soneraigntie</hi> but <hi>Tyrannie</hi>—. Againe, <hi>Obedience,</hi> vpon diſtaſt, is apt to murmure, and growes mutinous, and ſo 'tis no more a <hi>ſubiect,</hi> but a <hi>Rebell;</hi> where they kiſſe mutually, there is both ſtrength and ſafetie; but where they ſcold and iarre, all growes to ruine and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion. And this holds not onely in matters Ciuill, but in thoſe more ſacred. <hi>Command</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen preſuppoſes in vs an obedience no leſſe of neceſſitie, than will, and in God, inſallibilitie both of power, and incouragement. Faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of reſolution, or excuſe, in his high deſignements, are but the Teltales of a perfunctory zeale, howeuer they pretend to baſhfulneſſe, or humilitie.<note place="margin">Ier. 1.</note> 
               <hi>I cannot ſpeake Lord,</hi> or, <hi>I am vnworthy,</hi> were but courſe apologies of thoſe that vſed them, when God had either matter for their emploiment, or time; And the <hi>Quis ego Domine?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1. Exod. 3.</note> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> here, finds ſo little of approbation, that it meetes a checke; the Text will tell you in what heate and tumult, with an— <hi>Accenſus furor Iehonae</hi> the anger of the <hi>Lord</hi> was kindled againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> and it ſhould ſeeme,<note place="margin">Cap. 4.4.</note> in ſuch violence, that <hi>Abulenſis,</hi> after much trauerſe,<note place="margin">Toſt. in cap. <hi>4.</hi> Exod.</note> and diſpute makes that tergiuerſation of his little leſſe than a <hi>mortall ſinne,</hi> &amp; ſome of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> haue ſtrangely pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh't it, <hi>with the loſſe of Canaan,</hi> perſwading vs, the maine reaſon why he came not thither, was his backwardneſſe in obeying this—<hi>proficiſcere, Goe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Perer. in Exod.</note> But that's a <hi>Thalmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall</hi> and wilde fancie, fitter for ſuch giddy enrolements than the eares of a learned throng. And as <hi>Moſes</hi> may not but obey when God layes his command on him, ſo hee muſt not <hi>goe</hi> without it. <hi>Matthew</hi> muſt be <hi>called
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1984:6"/>from his receipt of cuſtome;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 9 9. Gal. 1.5.</note> &amp; he is not honor'd with a true Apoſtleſhip, who wants his —<hi>vocatus ſicut Aaron.</hi> That of God to the Pſeudo-prophets, was a fearefull Irony, — <hi>I ſent them not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 14.</note> 
               <hi>but they ranne</hi>—, voluntaries (it ſhould ſeeme) find here neither countenance, nor entertaine ment, but whom God hath preſt and ſealed to this great warfare; yet the other, notwithſtanding, in the field, and ſeaſoned once in battell, the retrait is more dangerous, than the aduenture.</p>
            <p>We finde <hi>Eſay</hi> more actiue and forward than any of the <hi>Prophets,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay cap. 6.</note> &amp; yet that ſpontaneouſneſſe not chid; who (as if he would anticipate the care and choiſe of God in his owne affaires) makes a haſty tender of his ſeruice,<note place="margin">Eſay cap. 5</note> with an — <hi>Ecce ego,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay cap. 8</note> 
               <hi>mitte me;</hi> yet, he had his former con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſions, and pangs too of feare, and diffidence; <hi>Woe is me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay cap. 5</note> 
               <hi>for I am a man of polluted lips.</hi> But ſee how God hammers and workes what he intends to file, either in perſon,<note place="margin">Eſay cap. 7</note> or by ſubſtitute? an <hi>Altar</hi> muſt be the <hi>Forge,</hi> and a <hi>Seraphin</hi> the <hi>workeman,</hi> who with his <hi>tongs ready,</hi> and <hi>his coale burning,</hi> ſhall both <hi>touch</hi> thoſe iniquities, and <hi>purge them,</hi> and then, and not till then, <hi>heere am I, Lord, ſend me.</hi> As therefore to ſtand ſtill, when God ſends out his <hi>proficiſcere,</hi> argues a ruſtie and ſullen lazineſſe, ſo to runne when he ſends not, arrogancie, and preſumption. That zeale is beſt qualified, which hath the patience to expect God's <hi>ſummons,</hi> and then the boldneſſe to doe his errand.</p>
            <p>The Schooleman in his 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. <hi>2ae.</hi> 185. <hi>queſtion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aqui. <hi>2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>.</hi> 2ae. qu. <hi>185.</hi> art. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> being to deale of religious perſons, ſtraines not the <hi>Myter</hi> from his diſcourſe, but moderates the <hi>quaere</hi> by diuiding it, and thinkes to take away <hi>all</hi> ſcruple by making <hi>two, whether it be lawfull to deſire Eccleſiaſticall honour</hi> (Epiſcopall hee Epithites) <hi>or to refuſe it being enioyned?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. de Val. in loc. Aqui. diſt. <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> par. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gregorie de Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia</hi> (his <hi>Amanuenſis</hi> here) turnes the perſpectiue from the <hi>obiect</hi> vpon the <hi>Agent,</hi> viewing as well the <hi>partie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring</hi> as the <hi>thing deſired,</hi> where, though hee deſcrie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1984:6"/>
               <hi>height of ſufficiency in perſonall endowments:</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaer. </seg>1</label> one <hi>Cap-A-Pe, in all points canonicall.</hi> yet he allowes not <hi>a baite for his eager appetite to feed on;</hi> a diſopinion'd vnder-valued man may <hi>not deſire it for the dignity,</hi> nor he that's fortune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troden <hi>for the reuenue.</hi> Be the perſon otherwiſe ne're ſo compleatly accommodated, yet the <hi>irregularity in his appetite ſtrangles his other eminencies, and ſo he is (at once) vnworthy, and vncapable. Reaſon</hi> and <hi>conſcience,</hi> will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troth <hi>Honours</hi> to <hi>deſert,</hi> which yet they <hi>diuorce</hi> from the <hi>immodeſty</hi> and <hi>heate</hi> of the deſire; for, if <hi>ſuper-intendencie be in the appetite more than the office, 'tis preſumption. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinas</hi> doth cenſur't ſo, a common practiſe of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, reproou'd in the Diſciples;<note place="margin">Aquinas vt ſup.</note> 
               <hi>Ye know their Princes loue to dominere,</hi> Mat. 20. <hi>if the honour be ſuperiour, 'tis ambition, and ſo meerely phariſaicall, — They loue the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt roomes at feaſts, and chiefe ſeats at Synagogues,</hi> Matth. 23. If the <hi>reuenue,</hi> it allies to <hi>couetouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 23.</note> and differs from the ſinne of <hi>Simon Magus</hi> thus, he proffer'd money for the gifts, theſe couet the gifts for the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</p>
            <p>On the other ſide, to reiect the <hi>Ephod</hi> wherewith au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority would inueſt thee, checkes doubly the refuſer, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Quaer. </seg>2</label> in waies of <hi>charity, humility. Charity ſeekes no more her own,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin. &amp; Greg. vt ſup.</note> 
               <hi>than her neighbours good;</hi> now the charity we owe vnto our ſelues, prompts vs to ſearch out —<hi>Otium ſanctum</hi> (as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> phraſes it) a holy vacancie from theſe pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like cures, but that to the Church bindes vs to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe. —<hi>Negotium iuſtum,</hi> the impoſition of any iuſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment,<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>19.</hi> de Ciuil. Dei cap. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> —<hi>quam ſarcinam ſi nullus imponit, intuendae vacandum eſt veritati, ſi autem imponitur, ſuſtinenda eſt propter charitatis neceſſitatem,</hi> the Father in his 19. <hi>de Ciuil. Dei. cap.</hi> 19. Againe, <hi>humility</hi> tie's vs in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Superiours, ſo that as often as we diſobey them we doe oppugneit, and this (in reſpect of God) is not <hi>meekneſſe,</hi> but <hi>pertinacy,—Tunc ante Dei oculos vera eſt humilitas, cum ad reſpuendum hoc quod vtiliter ſubire prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magn Gregor. <hi>1.</hi> pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Paſt. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:1984:7"/>
               <hi>pertinax non eſt—, Gregory</hi> 1. part of his Paſtorals 6. Chapter.</p>
            <p>To auoide then all occaſions of publike ſeruice for the Church, vnder a pretence of humility or recluſeneſſe, ſpeakes (too broadly) the delinquent, <hi>refractarie.</hi> Your <hi>Anchoret</hi> that digges his graue in <hi>ſpeculation</hi> meerely, and your Moale that is earth'd wholy in an affected ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarineſſe, are not liable ſo properly to <hi>obſcurity,</hi> as <hi>death;</hi> ſuch <hi>elaboratnes</hi> tends not to <hi>perfection,</hi> but <hi>diſeaſe;</hi> &amp; we finde an <hi>Apoplexy,</hi> and <hi>ſleepe,</hi> no leſſe on their <hi>endeauours</hi> than in their <hi>name;</hi> all knowledge is duſted with them, and 'tis no more a <hi>nurſerie</hi> of vertues, but a <hi>Tombe.</hi> And (indeed) ſuch <hi>Silkewormes</hi> ſpin themſelues into <hi>Flies,</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>animate, heartleſſe <hi>Flies,</hi> life neither for <hi>Church,</hi> nor <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</hi> The Laurell and honour of all ſecular de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes is the execution, and the happineſſe of thoſe ſacred ones is not intail'd barely to the <hi>knowledge</hi> of them, but to the <hi>fac &amp; vines.</hi> And that, not at <hi>home</hi> onely, in thy particular intendments, but <hi>abroad</hi> alſo in thy ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the Church; ſo that he that retraits at any Ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum or ſummons of his God, for the common affaires of the Church, to hugge and enioy himſelfe in his ſolitary ends, runnes himſelfe on the ſhelues of a rough cenſure, that of the Father to his <hi>Dracontius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Athan. in Epiſt. ad Drac. Epiſc. fugient. pars <hi>2.</hi> editio vltima.</note> —<hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ereor ne dum propter te fugis, propter alios ſis in periculo apud Dominum.</hi> To ſtand by, and giue aime onely, whil'ſt others ſhoote, and thou thy ſelfe no markman, proclaimes thy lazineſſe, if not thy impotency. What a <hi>nothing</hi> is thy <hi>arme?</hi> thy <hi>bowe?</hi> thy <hi>ſhaft?</hi> if not <hi>practiſed,</hi> not <hi>bent,</hi> not <hi>drawne vp?</hi> or if ſo glorious a marke, the <hi>Church?</hi> why not <hi>leueld</hi> at? either ſhe muſt be vnworthy of thy trauell, or thine of her. If therefore this thy Mother implore thy aide (ſo <hi>Auguſtine</hi> counſels his <hi>Eudoxius</hi>) on the one ſide,<note place="margin">Auguſt. Epiſt. <hi>81.</hi>
               </note> hand not with ambition; on the other, leane not to a lazie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſall, <hi>weigh not thine owne idleneſſe with the neceſſities and greatneſſe of her burthens, to which (whiles ſhe is in trauell)
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1984:7"/>if no good men will adminiſter their helpe, Certè quomodo naſecremini non inueniretis;</hi> God muſt then inuent new waies for our new birth: the Father in his 81. Epiſtle <hi>ad Edoxium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee then our <hi>Moſes</hi> may not haſtily thruſt himſelfe vpon thoſe weighty deſignes without authority and commiſſion from his God, and yet once ſummon'd, not recoile; but thus hauing his <hi>Congedeleere</hi> and warrant from aboue, wee muſt now account him in the place of God, <hi>God indeed,</hi> with a—<hi>ſicut</hi>—the Text tels vs ſo, thrice tels vs ſo, <hi>God to Aaron, God to Iſrael, God to Pharaoh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 3.4, 5.</note> 'Twere then too high a ſacriledge to rob him of any title or prerogatiue, which ſhould waite on the greatneſſe of ſuch a perſon. Let's giue him (what all ages haue) <hi>Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of place, Office, their attendants, Honour, Reuenue.</hi> I ſhall dwell my houre with the two firſt, with the latter on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>in Tranſitu,</hi> and vpon <hi>the by,</hi> they being inuolued in the two former. And that I may punctually go on, I will touch firſt (where I ſhould) with the <hi>Eminency—Goe.</hi>—</p>
            <p>Which as it was ſacred in the firſt inſtaulement,<note place="margin">Eminen. <hi>1.</hi> par.</note> ſo in the propagation moſt honourable to the times of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens.</hi> For <hi>Tertullian</hi> (ſpeaking of the magnificence and pompe which attended their ſuperſtitions) tels vs,<note place="margin">Tert. de Coron. militis cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>their doores, and Hoaſts, and Altars, and dead,</hi> and (what glorifies all) <hi>their Prieſts were crown'd:</hi> in his <hi>Corona mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litis cap.</hi> 10. And the firſt <hi>crowne</hi> which the <hi>Romanes</hi> v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, was their <hi>ſpicea Corona,</hi> giuen as a religious enſigne in honour of their <hi>Prieſts,—Honoſque is, non niſi vita fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plin. lib. <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; exules etiam, captoſque comitatur</hi> —ſayes my <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian,</hi> nought but death could terminate this honour, which was their companion both in <hi>exile,</hi> and <hi>captinity.</hi> They wore the name of <hi>Aruales Sacerdotes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alex. ab. Alex. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> firſt inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Romulus,</hi> and <hi>Acca Laurentia,</hi> his Nurſe, who, of her twelue Sonnes hauing loſt one, he himſelfe made vp the number with that title. But here's not all, —<hi>Termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum ſacrorum, &amp; finium, iurgijs terminandis praeerant,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1984:8"/>&amp; interueniebant,</hi> they were the <hi>peace-makers</hi> of the time, and ſate as Arbitrators in matters of conteſtation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man and man,<note place="margin">Plin. vt ſup.</note> as the great Naturaliſt in the 18. booke of his Hiſtory, 2. chapter. And who fitter for ſuch a morall office than the <hi>Prieſt?</hi> an <hi>honour</hi> which theſe worſt of times allow him, though with ſome turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, and indignation:<note place="margin">Numb. 16.3.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes and Aaron, you take too much vpon you,</hi> was the crie of a <hi>Iew</hi> once, ſo 'tis now, who would manacle and confine them onely to an <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticke power,</hi> and deueſt them quite of any <hi>ciuill au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> though <hi>Moſes</hi> here had both. But 'twas not without ſome ſhew of <hi>myſterie,</hi> that in the <hi>robes of Aaron</hi> (I inſtance now in him, leſt perchance they ſhould cauill with his brother <hi>Moſes</hi>) <hi>there was a crowne ſet vpon the Myter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 29.6.</note> moralizing a poſſible coniunction at leaſt of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and Magiſtrate in one perſon. And <hi>Chytraeus</hi> hath a patheticall obſeruation from the Apoſtles <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>— <hi>deuide aright,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>2 Tim. 2.</hi> Chyt. de ordin. miniſt. pag. <hi>506.</hi>
               </note> that the Metaphor was firſt taken from the manner of <hi>cutting</hi> or <hi>deuiding</hi> the <hi>members of the hoſt,</hi> Leuit. 7. where the <hi>fat and kidneies were burnt as a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to God, but the breaſt and the ſhoulder were giuen to the Prieſts:</hi> the Allegorie carries with it both weight and maieſty, here's a <hi>breaſt</hi> for <hi>counſell,</hi> and a <hi>ſhoulder</hi> for <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation</hi> in matters of <hi>gouernment.</hi> And no doubt in times of old (euen theſe of the Fathers) <hi>the Sacerdotall power,</hi> was at a great height, in equall ſcale with that of their honour,<note place="margin">Si Regum fulgori &amp; principum Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ademati inſerius eſt quam ſi plumbi metallum ad auri fulgorem compares, Ambr. ibid.</note> which was ſo eminent, that Saint <hi>Ambroſe rankes</hi> not the <hi>Myter</hi> with the <hi>Diadem,</hi> but in a <hi>zealous Hyperbole</hi> (pardon the Epithite) <hi>preferres it,</hi> and makes this comparatiuely to the other <hi>as a ſparkle to a flame, or dull Lead to burniſht Gold,</hi> in his <hi>de dignitate Sacerdotali cap.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>I may not follow the Father in his <hi>prieſtly Panegiricke,</hi> 'tis too high, and borders too much on the diſcipline of the <hi>triple crowne,</hi> ſuch a crowne as ne're yet girt the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>King</hi> or <hi>Prieſt,</hi> but of him that tramples on the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1984:8"/>
               <hi>necke of both;</hi> let ſuch inſolence inuade the right of <hi>Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tates,</hi> and ſpurne their <hi>Crownes</hi> and <hi>Scepters</hi> in the duſt, whil'ſt we ſeate our <hi>Aaron</hi> at the becke of <hi>Moſes,</hi> but the people too at that of <hi>Aaron:</hi> Let the <hi>Prieſthood doe obeyſance,</hi> and kiſſe the feet of <hi>Soueraignty;</hi> but let not the <hi>Laity</hi> turne the heele, and kicke againſt the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credneſſe of <hi>Prieſthood.</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> vpon theſe words of God to <hi>Moſes, —Tu eris illi in ijs quae ad Deum. —Hee ſhall be to thee in ſtead of a mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 4.16.</note> 
               <hi>and thou ſhalt be to him in ſtead of God,</hi> ſeemes entranc'd awhile, and bringing them to the ballance, and weighing preciſely euery ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, cries out,<note place="margin">Aug. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Exod. <hi>10.</hi> quaeſt.</note> 
               <hi>Magnum Sacramentum cuius figuram ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</hi> as if <hi>Moſes</hi> were a <hi>medium betweene God and Aaron, and Aaron betweene Moſes and the people.</hi> The morall is plaine, <hi>Soueraignty ſtands betweene God and the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and the Prieſthood betweene Soueraignty and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> Howeuer the Ceremonies due to either heretofore, in matters of Inſtaulement, ſtood not at ſuch <hi>enmity</hi> as we can ſay <hi>they differ'd,</hi> they were both <hi>anoynted,</hi> and both <hi>crown'd;</hi> and though the authority were vnequall in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of <hi>place,</hi> yet not of <hi>employment, Yee are full of power by the ſpirit of the Lord,</hi> Micah. 3.8. And <hi>Eliſha</hi> could once tell the King, <hi>He ſhould know there was a Prophet in Iſrael,</hi> 2 King. 5.8. And in matters of preſeruation God was as zealous for the ſafety of theſe as them, —<hi>Touch not mine anointed, and doe my Prophets no harme,</hi> Pſal. 105.</p>
            <p>But let not my <hi>zeale</hi> to the <hi>Prieſt</hi> diſpriuiledge my <hi>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagiance</hi> to my <hi>King.</hi> I ſpeake not this to ſet vp <hi>Moſes</hi> in competition with <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> or riuall the dignity of the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> with that of <hi>Soueraignty;</hi> but to mind you in what luſtre it ſometimes ſhin'd, &amp; how the times now conſpire to cloud that glory.</p>
            <p>The dayes haue beene, when the <hi>Laicke</hi> was ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, not onely of the <hi>title</hi> of a <hi>Prieſt,</hi> but the <hi>office:</hi> for <hi>Euſebius</hi> examples in many of them, who thruſting vpon Biſhops of primitiue times, <hi>Statim concionandi munus
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1984:9"/>obierunt,</hi> in his <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 15. And <hi>Tertullian</hi> (ſpeaking of the inſolencies and taunts which the <hi>Laity</hi> then put vpon the <hi>Prieſthood</hi>) tells vs that they <hi>iuſtified</hi> their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice &amp; iniuries to the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> by <hi>vſurping the name,</hi> or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning rather,<note place="margin">Te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. lib. de Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nog. cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> —<hi>Quum extollimur &amp; inflamur aduerſus clerum, tunc omnes Sacerdotes, quia Sacerdotes nos Deo, &amp; Patri fecit, quum ad peraequationem diſciplinae Sacerdotalis prouocamur, deponimus infulas, &amp; pares ſumus;</hi> in his booke <hi>de Monogamia, cap.</hi> 12.</p>
            <p>It ſhould ſeeme then the <hi>office</hi> and <hi>name</hi> paſt honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly through all ages, euen thoſe of <hi>Infidels,</hi> though the <hi>perſon</hi> were ſometimes expoſed to the perſecutions of the time, and ſuffered vnder the blaſphemies of vnchriſtian tongues; but now the very <hi>title</hi> growes barbarous, and he thinkes he hath wittily diſcountenanced the greatnes of the calling, that can baffle the <hi>profeſſour</hi> with the name of <hi>Prieſt.</hi> But theſe, whil'ſt they intend to wound, they honour vs, and wee account them no ſcarres, but <hi>glories.</hi> Let ſuch children mocke on the Prophet, the euent (I beleeue) will proue as horrid as that of old, will you trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to heare it ſpoken? you may reade it then, and look pale too, in 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.24.</p>
            <p>May it pleaſe you now,<note place="margin">Office 2.</note> turne your eyes from the <hi>dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> and reflect vpon the <hi>office.</hi> The <hi>office,</hi> a taske indeed, ſuch a one as ſhould rather prouoke our <hi>endeauours,</hi> than <hi>appetites. If any man deſire the office of a Biſhop</hi> (let's a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while leaue the word <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and faſten vpon this, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority may beare it out the better) <hi>deſires a good worke,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.1.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.1. <hi>Lib.</hi> 19. <hi>Ciuit. Dei cap.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>Quia nomen operis eſt, non honoris</hi> (as <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> gloſſes it) 'tis a name of <hi>worke,</hi> not <hi>honour;</hi> a <hi>worke</hi> no leſſe fearefull, than laborious, no where better figur'd than by <hi>Moſes,</hi> here, to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> repriuing <hi>Iſrael</hi> from <hi>Egypt,</hi> from which 'tis ſcarce any way differenc'd, but in the difficulty, and therein it exceeds the <hi>type;</hi> difficulty worthy the trauells of the beſt, were not thoſe labours
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1984:9"/>ſhoulder'd and thruſt on by vaine-glory.<note place="margin">Greg. de Val. in <hi>2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>.</hi> 2ae. disp. <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>3.</hi> part. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iſtaec cathedra cupientem ſe, &amp; audacter expetente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, non requirit, ſed orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, ſed eruditum</hi>—. So <hi>Valentia</hi> vpon <hi>Aquine.</hi> —This <hi>chaire of Moſes</hi> is no ſeat of ambition, but deſert, it hates either an intruder, or purſuer; He that gaines it by coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, or bold deſire, doth not poſſeſſe, but inuade it, and 'tis not ſo much his by right of inheritance, as vſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation.</p>
            <p>Theſe honors ſawne onely vpon humble worths, men clad &amp; harneſſed with double eminencie, of life, of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, thoſe whoſe vertues haue aduanc'd them aboue the ordinary leuell and pitch of popularity. Yet to theſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without this <hi>proficiſcere</hi>— to <hi>Moſes, Goe. Clemens</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle, will perſwade you: <hi>'tis the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of Saint Peter. Auguſtine</hi> goes farther,<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>19.</hi> de Ciuit. Dei, cap. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> —<hi>Locus ſuperior ſine quo populus regi non poteſt, etſi adminiſtretur vt decet, tamen indecenter appetitur</hi>—. Suppoſe the man wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of this place of <hi>Eminencie,</hi> &amp; comes home in matters of <hi>adminiſtration,</hi> yet he is to blame in thoſe of <hi>appetite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. de Val. vt ſupra.</note> for the <hi>deſire</hi> laies open his <hi>vnworthineſſe,</hi> and the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man will not flatter him, but concludes it plainely for <hi>a mortall ſinne.</hi> And if we may gueſſe at the child by the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, it beſt countenanceth <hi>leuity,</hi> or <hi>arogance,</hi> neuer read to be the proper ſeedes of any vertue. Notwithſtanding this <hi>deſire</hi> (ſometimes) comes not within the compaſſe of preſumption, if the <hi>worke</hi> be the obiect of our appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tite, and not the <hi>honour,</hi> or, if the <hi>honour,</hi> not the <hi>reuenew,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Part. <hi>1.</hi> Paſtor. cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> — <hi>Appetere calſitudinem Epiſcopalem, non eſt ſemper prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptio, ſed appetere Epiſcopatum, ratione celſitudinis. ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petit enim celſitudinem, ſupra dignitatem— Gregorie</hi> will haue it ſo. Howeuer, if it pleaſe you to glance on my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer quotation from the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1 Tim 3.1.</note> 'twill not ſo much whet your appetite, as grauell it; for firſt <hi>Beza</hi> limits the deſire, <hi>If any man deſire?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Beza in licum.</note> and 'tis not meant —<hi>de ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu</hi>— of the appetite, or ambition to get the See, but <hi>de animo,</hi> of the earneſt deſire to benefit the Church, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1984:10"/>the words will carry that interpretation, yet the commendation which is annexed truces with the <hi>worke,</hi> not the <hi>deſire, —Bonum opus deſider at</hi>—, not —<hi>benè deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derat</hi>—, though it be good what he deſires, yet hee doth not well to deſire it. Men vnworthy of what they ſue for, onely becauſe they ſue for it. And this in Primitiue times hath occaſioned in many no leſſe a modeſtie than vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſſe in thoſe ſacred vndertakings, when the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, with a kind of reluctancie and feare, were towed on to theſe high imployments. Nay ſome, whether through maieſtie of the place, or roughneſſe of the times, or guilt of their owne weakeneſſe, haue panted and breath'd ſhort in their deſires to this great enterpriſe, and at length ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chang'd the honour for an exile.<note place="margin">Greg. Naz in praeſat. Apol. Athan. in epiſt. ad Dracont. Epiſt. fug. vt Gloſſ. in prim. Euan. Marc.</note> 
               <hi>Nazianzen</hi> flies into <hi>Pontus; Dracontius,</hi> into the skirts of <hi>Alexandria:</hi> and it is tradition'd me by <hi>Aquinas.</hi> (and he quotes Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> for it) that Saint <hi>Marke cut off his thumbe, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Sacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotio reprobus haberetur</hi>— They are the Schoolemans owne words in his 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. <hi>2ae. quaeſt.</hi> 185. <hi>Artic.</hi> 1. But 'twill not be amiſſe here to take Saint <hi>Ambroſe —quamnis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum—</hi> with vs; that theſe things were done in the Churches great extremities, when he that was —<hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in preſbyterio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Part. <hi>2.</hi> paſt. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> was —<hi>primus in Martyrio.</hi> 'Twould require the temper of a braue <hi>reſolution,</hi> and a better <hi>zeale,</hi> to <hi>deſire</hi> this <hi>Bonum opus,</hi> when 'twas made the touchſtone and furnace of mens faith and conſtancie, not only in leading others to the ſtake, but their own ſuffering where they were to be a voluntary <hi>Holocauſt,</hi> and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to the Church, there to remaine a monument of their <hi>Religion,</hi> and others <hi>tyranny.</hi> 'Tis true, Hiſtories haue fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht vs with examples of ſome which haue renounc'd an Empire, and (which is ſtrange) a Popedome; <hi>Diocleſian</hi> did one, and <hi>Celeſtinus,</hi> t'other. The times (we may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe) were bluſtring, and the reuenewes thin at <hi>Rome,</hi> when the honor of the chaire, was at once not deſir'd and ſcorn'd. No proiect now vnſifted, no ſtratagem vndig'd
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1984:10"/>for; no reach of policie vnfathom'd for the compaſſing of that great <hi>See,</hi> though by ſyniſter, though by diuelliſh attempt, nay, that's the chiefe engine by which it works. <hi>Tiberius</hi> could once tell a Prince of the <hi>Celts,</hi> that <hi>Rome had a ſword for her conqueſt, not an Apothecaries ſhop;</hi> now they are both too little; <hi>Sword, and poyſon, and maſſacre, and Piſtoll, and knife, and powder,</hi> for the purchaſe (or at leaſt the ſtrengthening) of the <hi>triple crowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I would Machiauell had rendeuouz'd only in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuited Territories, and not knockt at the gates of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Dominions; 'tis to be fear'd he hath Factors neerer home, thoſe which not onely know the backdoores to the Staffe, and Myter, but are acquainted with the locke, which if they cannot force or picke by the finger of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie or greatneſſe, they turne with that golden key which at once opens a way to a purchas'd honour, and a ruine.</p>
            <p>Ambition whither wilt thou? nay, where wilt thou not? to the pinacle of the Temple for the glory of the world, though thou tumble for it to thy eternall ruine.</p>
            <p>The Greeke Philoſopher will beg of the gods, that <hi>he may behold the Sunne ſo neere, as to comprehend the forme,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eudoxus.</note> 
               <hi>beautie, greatneſſe of it, and afterwards he cares not if hee burne,</hi> as if there were no ſuch Martyrdome, as what <hi>Ambition</hi> fires. <hi>Occidar modò imperet</hi>—,<note place="margin">Tacit. Annals.</note> was the reſolution of <hi>Agrippina</hi> for her <hi>Nero;</hi> but loe, how the euent crownes the vnſatiateneſſe of her deſires? He gaines the kingdome, and firſt dig'd out thoſe bowels which had foſtered him, and then that heart which was the throne of ſuch an aſpiring thought; cruelty ſhall I call it, or iuſtice, when the vaineglory of the mother was penanc'd with the vnnaturalneſſe of the ſon. Thus loftie mindes (furniſht with a ſtrong hope of the ſucceſſe of their deſignes) haue embark't themſelues into great acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and propoſing humane ends, as ſcales to their high thoughts, haue bin wafted into ſtrange promotions, but after they haue (a while) ſpangl'd in that their firmament
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:1984:11"/>of honour, they become falling ſtarres, and ſo the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe prooues as inglorious as the enterpriſe was bold, and deſperate. We haue ſeldome met with any eminency that was ſodaine and permanent: Thoſe which in their <hi>dawne</hi> of <hi>Fortune breake</hi> ſo gloriouſly, meet with a ſtorme at <hi>noone,</hi> or elſe a <hi>cloud</hi> at <hi>night.</hi> The Sunne that riſes in a <hi>grey</hi> and <hi>ſullen</hi> morne, <hi>ſets</hi> cleareſt; and indeed <hi>ambition</hi> is too haſtie, and is hurried violently to the end it aimes at without cautelouſneſſe and circumſpection to the meane; but humilitie hath a calme and temperate pace, and ſtoopes it along in a gentle poſture, yet at length at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines her marke, but ſlowly, as if it went vnwilling to honour, and ſlighted thoſe proffers which others ſue for. <hi>I enuie Scipio Africanus, and Marcus Portius</hi> (you know whoſe 'tis, <hi>Traianus</hi> to <hi>Plutarch</hi>) <hi>more for contempt of offices. than the victories they haue wonne, becauſe a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour for the moſt part is in Fortunes power, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of offices liu'd in prudence.</hi> Will you heare the para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe? <hi>Tacitus</hi> giue's it, <hi>Sapientibus cupido gloriae nouiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. exuitur</hi>—. Wiſemen are ſo little in the drift of honor that they loath the ſent, 'tis the vanitie, they laſt put off, and there was a time when a modeſt refuſall of them, was no by-way to them; for this ſhadow once followed, flies, but fled,<note place="margin">Chryſ. Hom. <hi>35.</hi> in Matth.</note> followes—<hi>primatus fugientem deſiderat, deſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum borret,</hi> ſaies the Father. 'Tis a tricke of primacie to fawne where 'tis not croocht too, but looke coy where it's ouer courted, like ſome weather-cocks which in a conſtant and churliſh wind beake fairely towards vs, but in a wanton blaſt, turne taile.</p>
            <p>Hence it is that in matters of authoritie, and prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence, pride hath for the moſt part the foile, humilitie the conqueſt, that ſtoopes baſely to the title, or the profit, and looſes either, This in a modeſt diſtance keepes a loofe, till worth inuite it, and at length gaines both; ſo that it is in wayes of promotion, as in ſome water-works, where one Engine raiſes it to make it fall more violently,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1984:11"/>another beats it downe that it might mount higher.<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.6.</note> The aduiſe then of S. <hi>Peter</hi> comes ſeaſonably here, —<hi>Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your ſelues vnder the mighty hand of God, that hee may exalt you in due time.</hi> The words are not without their ſtrength of emphaſis, here is an—<hi>humiliamini</hi>—erown'd with an —<hi>vt exaltet,</hi> humble your ſelues, that he <hi>may</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt, as if <hi>humilitie</hi> were ſo neceſſary a diſpoſition to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, that without it God might not exalt. But ſoft, Impoſtor; Thou which iugleft both with God and with the times, I call not that <hi>bumility</hi> which is typ'd in the downefall of the looke, or the affected crindge and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture of the bodie; but the knee of the inward man, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the Wiſeman of old called <hi>the character of an holy ſoule, leading noble harts ſlowly to the feaſts of friends, but ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their ſuccour in calamities;</hi> So that true meekeneſſe is retinu'd with a double worth, <hi>charity, reſolution;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plato in Timaeo.</note> And the Philoſopher will tell you, 'tis <hi>Avertue belongs to the couragious part of the ſoule, ſeated betweene two baſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treames, Puſillanimity, Arrogance,</hi> No <hi>Buffone,</hi> and yet no <hi>Bafler,</hi> ſupporting ſometimes iniuries, not our of <hi>cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardice,</hi> but <hi>Patience,</hi> allaying all tumults and inſtigations of the ſoule to <hi>reuenge</hi> or <hi>choller,</hi> not expos'd to any vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of paſſion, but as <hi>temperate</hi> in diſpoſition, as <hi>ſetled;</hi> no waue in her deſigne, nor tempeſt in her thought; ſhe is all calme, not a wind ſo rough as to moue a ſtorme either in her minde or action. But there is a <hi>ſquint-eiea humilitie,</hi> which caſts one way, and points another; the looke is deiected, ſtill groueling towards the earth, and with ſuch a dreſſe of mortification, as if it deſired no more of it, than would ſerue it for a graue; when the thought meaſures out a Dioceſſe, or labours on ſome greater proiect, which gain'd the countenance is chear'd, the bodie droopes not, and he can now ſafely icſt it with that old Abbot,
<q>
                  <l>Quaerebam prius claues monaſterij,</l>
                  <l>Quibus inuentis, nunc rectus incedo.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:1984:12"/>
            <p>And this ſubtle Nauigator neuer ſteeres as be ſets his compaſſe; the looke (haply) poines you to a formall meekeneſſe, but the thought ſtill coaſts vpon Ambition; yet this gluttonous <hi>deſire</hi> ſeldome anchors any where, but goes on ſtill with a full ſaile, till 't'ath compaſſed the cape tis bound for,<note place="margin">Sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ca.</note> —<hi>Habet boc vitium omnis ambitio, non reſpicit,</hi> The thirſt of Eminencie is headſtrong, and runs with a looſe bridle. 'Tis to ſee much below ſatietie, that it ſtill deſires, nay 'tis hungry euen in ſurfet, and is ſharpen'd with the fruition of that it couered; ſo that the birth of this title is but the conception of another, one honour roomes not the greatneſſe of his thought, our <hi>Aaron</hi> is not contented with an <hi>Ephod, the rod of Moſes,</hi> would doe well too; Authoritie is ſleighted, diſcipline falne, and corruption crept ſtrangely into the times, but</p>
            <p>—<hi>O fortunatam me conſule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iuuers. Sat. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Romam.</hi> What ſhould a mercifull worth doe with a Conſulſhip? 'tis a place for thunder, not clemencie, one that can ſtrike dead exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancie with the furrowes of the brow, and quell all vice with the tempeſt of a looke, one that can both vnſheath the ſword of authoritie, and brandiſh it, if not to <hi>reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> yet to <hi>ruine;</hi> Thus he would make gouernment the ſtale both of his pride and Tyranny, his proiects are lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily-cruell, ſo are his actions too, yet ſtill in a hot ſent of promotion, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> (if they want a trumpet for others com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation) ſhall borrow one from his owne, and ſo at once applaud his deſignes, and iuſtifie them. And indeed this titillation and itch of honour, if it once finde in the boſome of the receiuer a faire admittance, doth ſmooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſinuate and cheat vpon the powers of <hi>Reaſon.</hi> But when 'tis throughly ſeated and enthron'd there, 'tis no more a gueſt but a Tyrant, and leaues the poſſeſſor, not a maſter, but a captiue, and in this caſe, I know not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> will pittie his <hi>Aurelius,</hi> or excuſe him,<note place="margin">Aug. Eoiſt. <hi>64.</hi> ad Aurel.</note> —<hi>Erſi cuiquam facile ſit gloriam non cupere dum negatur, difficile eſt ea non delectari cum offertur</hi>—in his
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1984:12"/>64 Epiſtle. Howener the Father ſeemes there to pleade onely for the delight in glories offer'd, not in the vniuſt proſecution of thoſe denied. But our <hi>humble-arrogant</hi> walkes not to his <hi>temple of honour by that of vertue,</hi> but inuaſion; and of ſome of his <hi>colleagues,</hi> the Fathers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd of old, <hi>Qui nequaquam diuinitus vocati,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. part. <hi>1.</hi> paſt. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſed ſua cupiditate accenſi, culmen regiminr. rapiunt potiùs, quàm aſſequuntur</hi> 'Tis Saint <hi>Gregories</hi> line, and a ſtrong one too, ſuch a one as the Prophet once laſh't <hi>Iudah</hi> with,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 8.4.</note> 
               <hi>Ho.</hi> 8.4. <hi>They haue ſet vp a King but not by me, they would make a Ruler, I knew it not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23.</note> Would you haue a more punctuall character, that of the Phariſees is moſt appo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite: They loue greetings in the markets, and to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of men, <hi>Rabbi, Rabbi, Matth.</hi> 23.7. <hi>Deuout crnelty, Religious arrogance</hi> (the Father will make it out) <hi>Ob pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem miſeri, ob ſplendorem infalices,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Naz. in praefat. Apol. edit. lat.</note> in his Apologie firſt Oration 44. <hi>pag.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I haue followed <hi>Moſes</hi> too long as a Magiſtrate, I muſt now a while as a Prieſt, and (what I exchang'd him for) a Biſhop. I ſhall not trauell farre, c're I deſcry them both in a full careere, not farr from the roade I left the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, <hi>Ambition,</hi> but in a more couert, and vntroden way; a way, howeuer doubly obnoxious to the paſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, becauſe <hi>vnwarrantable,</hi> becauſe <hi>forbidden;</hi> no autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie for his progreſſe, no Letters patents from heauen, no <hi>proficiſcere</hi> from his God, <hi>Goe,</hi> yet he ruunes, runnes without command, nay againſt it, trebly againſt it, againſt that, <hi>non dominantes in clerum</hi>—, feed,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.3. Iam. 3.1.</note> But not as Lords ouer Gods heritage, but enſamples, and againſt that <hi>nolite magiſtrs,</hi> be not maſters, knowing you ſhall receiue the greater condemnation; nay againſt the direct prohibition of Chriſt to his Diſciples,<note place="margin">Matth 20.27.</note> —<hi>Will there be any great among you</hi>—, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>let him be your ſeruant.</hi> 'Tis high time then this bladder were a little prickt, and this impoſtume launc'd. The body of the Church deſire's it, cries for't, ſhee is ſicke, ſicke euen vnto death, yet no
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1984:13"/>Phyſitian in <hi>Iſrael</hi> will adminiſter, will? durſt not; Wee are growne ſo emaſculate, and palſie-ſtrooken, in waies of reprehenſion, the times ſo cenſorious, and in a luſt of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueltie, that this mount of God which was wont to ſend out lightnings and thunder to the Iſraelites below, is now growne a terrour to the <hi>Moſes</hi> that ſhall climbe it. And whereas the Pulpit hath beene formerly our Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall to iudge and ſentence the lapſes and deprauations of the people, they haue made at length a bar for our own ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignement, &amp; their doome or mercy paſſes on vs, as we ſhall pleaſe, or not pleaſe, but the verdict runnes much to the fancy of the cenſurer, which is commonly as barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and wilde, as he that giues it. Diſcourſes (and I am ſorry I cannot call them Sermons) are ſo ſleeke, and wooing for applauſe, the eares of the times ſo coy, and pickt for accurateneſſe, that to be plaine or home, entitles the ſpeaker to rudeneſſe or ſtoiciſme, each offer'd annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a barbariſme, and euery reproofe a libell. The hew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe of a glorious vice, or the whipping of a ſinne in ſcarler, <hi>Praemunires</hi> him that doth it, and hee growes a tributary and ſlaue to the frownes and diſhonours of the time,<note place="margin">Iuuen. Sat. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> —<hi>Vnde illa priorum—ſcribendi quodcunque ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo flagrante liberet—Simplieitas?</hi> 'T ſhould ſeeme An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie had a priuiledge of venting any thing that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the ſimplicitie and truth of an honeſt breaſt; But the thoughts of aftertimes were choak't with a —<hi>non andeo dicere</hi>—, ſincerity was turn'd bankrupt, and truth an exile, plaine-dealing, pertinacie, and zeale, madneſſe. But what, ſhall <hi>Moſes</hi> here be tongue-tyed, ſhall he ſtut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Meſſages of his God? —<hi>Quid refert dictis ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcat Mutius annon?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iu. ibid.</note> Puſillanimity and deiectedneſſe of ſpirit in the imployment of thy Maker, is the baſeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of cowardiſe; for my part, I haue ſet vp my reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with that of S. <hi>Bernard:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ad Fulc. Epiſt. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quid me loqui pudeat, quod illis non puduit facere? ſi pudeat audire quod impudenter egerunt, non pudeat emendare quod libenter non audiant.</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:1984:13"/>Let me tell howeuer this child of vaine-glory, that no touch of malecontentedneſſe, or ſpirit of inuection puts me on the iuſtice of theſe complaints; But that which the deuout Abbot cals, <hi>patient anger, humble indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> —euen that charity wherewith he carechiz'd his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious pupill, —<hi>Quae tibi condolet, quamuis non dolenti quae tibs miſeretur, licet non miſerabils, &amp; inde magis dolet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. ad Fule: epiſt. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quod cum ſis dolendus, non doles, &amp; inde magis miſeretur, quod cùm miſer ſis, miſerabilis non es, vult tetuum ſcire do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorem, vt iam non habeas vnde dolere, vnlt te tuam ſcire miſeriam, vt incipias miſer non eſſe,</hi> in his 2 Epiſtle, <hi>Ad Fulconem</hi>—.</p>
            <p>I neuer yet enuied the proſperity of any, I haue ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times wond'red at their waies of aduancement, and now haue trac't them, and finde a double ſtaire by which they aſcend, <hi>zeale, policie,</hi>—(pleaſe you to tranſlate the termes, you may, they will beare the chriſtning) <hi>Faction, Simo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> —, one of the chiefe meanes to gaine preferment, is, to crie downe the way to it. And he that will haue three li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, muſt firſt preach violently againſt two. Non-reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency muſt be a capitall and indiſpenſable crimes. Plura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, damn'd, till they be either offer'd, or poſſeſt, when the fiſh is caught, what makes the net here then? away with it; the queſtion is ſtated on to'ther ſide. <hi>A double Beneſice is but one liuing,</hi> and that ſwallowed with as little reluctation, as 'twas but now thundred againſt, with all the bitterneſſe that the power of virulence could ſuggeſt; all's well now, the conſcience is at peace, and (what is ſtrange) the tongue too. Ere long, Non-reſidency hangs not in the teeth, but that is eaſily put off, for the honour of <hi>Nicodemus,—To be a great Maſter in Iſrael,—Si vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landum ſit ius, regnandi causâ violandum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sueton.</note> —what matter's it for iuſtice ſo we gaine an Empire? or for equity ſo we may inſult? The application needs no skrew, 'twill come home of it's owne accord to the murmurings of the guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1984:14"/>boſome; In the meane time it much ſtaggers mee, to ſee the reconcilement of two vertuous friends with a baſe aduerſary? a Saint in the countenance, an Angell in the tongue, with an Hypocrite at the heart.</p>
            <p>Thus (beloued) vpon eaſie enquiry wee may as well deſcrie an equiuocation in the looke, as in the word, and he that can art it handſomely in wayes of diſſimulation, hath not ſo much two tongues, as two faces; one lookes towards the world, where demureneſſe laies on her paint and colour, and this oftentimes deludes, ſhamefully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ludes; the other towards heauen, and that's but courſely dawb'd in reſpect of it, for the eye of the Almighty can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be dazell'd, that will deſcrie her furrowes and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and at length giue her a reward anſwerable to the deſert, <hi>her portion with the Hypocrite,</hi> and there I leaue it.</p>
            <p>This fruitleſſe and pernicious branch prun'd, and lopt off, t'other buds, no leſſe dangerous than that, and yet more flouriſhing, it ſprouts now to ſuch a bredth and height, that it hath almoſt ouerſhadowed the body of the Church, inſomuch, that the Foules of the aire lodge in the branches thereof. No Vulture or Rauen (emblemes of rapine and greedineſſe) though they deuoure and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uock it (ſo they haue a tricke of merchandizing) but neſts and perches there; nay ſcarce an Owle or Buzzard (now the metaphors of dulneſſe and ſimplicity) but hoots and reuels there. Times more than calamitous, when the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance and patrimony of the Church ſhall be thus leas'd out to <hi>auarice</hi> and <hi>folly,</hi> when thoſe her honors w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſhe entailes vpon deſert, ſhall be heaped vpon a golden ignorant, who rudely treades on thoſe ſacred preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, without any warranted <hi>proſiciſcere</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God or man. We find <hi>Moſes</hi> trembling here, though encourag'd both by the perſwaſion &amp; command of the Almighty,—<hi>Et in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmus
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1984:14"/>quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vt honoris onus ſuſcipiat, anhelat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. par. <hi>1.</hi> paſt. cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; qui ad ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum valde vrgetur ex proprijs, humeru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> libenter opprimenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ponderibus ſubmittit alienis</hi>—. 'Tis <hi>Gregories</hi> complaint in the 1. part of his Paſtorall, chapter 7.</p>
            <p>Strange monument of weakneſſe. hee that reeles vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his owne burthen, ſtoopes to be oppreſt with the weight of others, and lot how he tumbles to <hi>a mortall ſinne</hi> (The Schoolemen doth ſtile it ſo) directly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to a paire of vertues, <hi>iuſtice, charity; vniuſt,</hi> that the reuenues due to worth ſhould be pack't vpon bulckleſſe and vnable perſons,<note place="margin">Greg. de Val. in <hi>2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. 2ae.</hi> Aqul. diſt. <hi>10.</hi> q. <hi>3</hi> punc. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>vncharitable</hi> for him to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the guidance and paſturing of a flocke who was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer train'd vp in the conditions of a ſhepherd. Neither is he an enemy onely of a double vertue, but a compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of two ſuch ſinnes which ſeeme to braue, and dare the Almighty to reuenge on the prophaner, <hi>Intruſion, periurie;</hi> firſt, in ruſhing on the profeſſion not legitimate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call'd, then in purchaſing her honours. Yet there are which can ſay with the Diſciple—<hi>Maſter we haue left all and followed thee</hi>—our birth-right for the Church; left did I ſay? ſold it, exchanged the poſſeſſions of our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (their vineyard) to purchaſe thine; and in ſtead of that peny which thou giueſt in liew of a Crowne and recompence to thy labourer, we haue giuen thouſands to be poſſeſt one, and ſo, thou not hiring vs, wee haue, it. But heare S. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſchooling his <hi>Eugenius,</hi> and doe not ſo much bluſh as tremble,—<hi>Quis mihi det,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern epiſt. <hi>238.</hi> ad Euge.</note> 
               <hi>antequam moriar videre eccleſiam Dei ſicut in diebus antiquis quandò Apoſtoli laxabant retia in capturam, non auri, ſed anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum! quàm cupio te illius haer: ditare vocem cuius adeptus es ſedem? Pecunia tua tecum in perditionem—. O vox to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitrui!</hi> The Abbot goes on deuoutly in the 238. Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>ad Eugenium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If that Father be too calme and modeſt in his reproofe,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1984:15"/>and cannot rouze bloud in the cheekes of the delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent: S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſhall ſtartle it, or elſe ſcare you with the viſion of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> or <hi>Gehazi,—Qui non timen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes illud Petri,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. de dign. ſacerd. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>aut Elizei, Sacerdotalem defamant ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem, ſanctique Epiſcopatus gratiam pecunijs coemerunt,</hi> in his <hi>de dignitate Sacerdotali cap.</hi> 5.</p>
            <p>And indeed, in waies of ſufficiency and worth, 'tis the —<hi>ſi nil attuleris</hi>—damp's the preferment; The age can inſtance, in ſome languiſhing and weake in their intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuals, men without ſap or kernell, who (hauing their ſtore-houſe well fraught with that <hi>white</hi> and <hi>red</hi> earth) haue ſtumbled on the glories of the time, as if for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune would make them happy in deſpight of vertue; when others of Chriſts followers (were truely his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples) are ſent abroad with their—<hi>ite &amp; praedicate—bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>footed, without bag or ſcrip,</hi> but their Commiſſion large —<hi>Omni creaturae</hi>—the wide world is their place of reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, no particular roofe to ſhelter them, or place of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiredneſſe to lay their head in. Nay ſome that haue ſeru'd a triple Apprentiſhip to Arts and Sciences, and ſpent in theſe our <hi>Athens</hi> the ſtrength of their time and patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, men throughly ballac'd for thoſe high deſignes, well kern'd both in yeeres and iudgement, lie mouldring for non-employment, and daſht for ſlowneſſe or promotion; when others of cheape and thin abilities, men without growth or bud of knowledge, haue met with the honours of aduancement, and trample on thoſe deiected booke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wormes which diſſolue themſelues into induſtry for the ſeruice of their Church, yet meet neither with her pompe, nor her reuenue; nay, ſome that haue waſted their Lampe, are burnt their Taper to an inch of yeeres, haue ſpent thoſe fortunes in the trauailes of Diuinity, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> would largely haue accommodated them for more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular courſes, and enforced to retire themſelues to the ſolitarineſſe of ſome ten-pound Cure, and ſo ſpin out
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1984:15"/>he hath ſuffer'd ſtrangely in the conſures of the world) ſomewhat windy, &amp; tempeſtuous, but ſuch as had autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity onely from the tongue, not the heart, and as ſoone ore-blowne, as occaſion'd, nought elſe but a greene leafe in a flame, crack't, ſparkled, and ſo out. His rule of friendſhip the beſt, not popular, but choice, &amp; there too, where it found truth, no gloſſe; there vnſhooke, nobly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant, his, both in his heart, &amp; in his purſe; not in his purſe, (as <hi>Seneca</hi> writes of <hi>Sicilius, where nought could be extracted but an hundred vpon a hundred</hi>) or as your <hi>Hackney</hi> Mynt-men for the moſt part doe, <hi>ten vpon the ſame number,</hi> but that trebled, many times, for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as the clemency of ſome vnperſecuting ſcroles can teſtifie. His contribution, and beneuolence in way of almes, rather powr'd out, than giuen, as if pouerty had beene the obiect of his profuſeneſſe, not of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe; yet that without froth of oſtentation, without reference to merit, on the grounds of a true charity. His Religion (wherein the world thought hee had wau'd and totter'd) vpon his accounts to God, and his inlargements and declarations to his friends, on his death-bed, faſt to the Church of <hi>England;</hi> which, (though in the laſt act) was beleager'd by ſome emaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate ſuggeſtions, yet, bleſſed be the circumſpection of a carefull Sonne, it ſtood vnbatter'd, and in that loialty, and ſtrength, he penitently gaue vp his ſoule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of his Redeemer.</p>
            <p>And now hee is <hi>gone,</hi> let his imperfections fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, and the memory of them rot, and moulder with his body; hee had many, ſome preualent; and (good Lord) which of vs haue not in a large pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion! But they are our <hi>earthy</hi> and <hi>duſty,</hi> and <hi>aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> part, ſo they were his; let them then be buried with him; ſhouell them into his graue; <hi>earth to earth, aſhes to aſhes, duſt to duſt;</hi> let them ſpring no more,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1984:16"/>to the ſoyling and diſhonour of his name, or our owne vncharitableneſſe, but let his aſhes reſt in peace; for hee is now—<hi>Gone to his long home, and the mourners haue walkt for him about the ſtreets.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Gloria in excelſis Deo.</hi> Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1984:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
